hi my name is Joe brewer and I want to
share with you another book that I've
read that is helpful for anyone trying
to create large scale social change by
looking at the patterns of culture this
book is called war and peace and war the
rise and fall of Empires by Peter
turchin Peter torsion is a population
ecologist so he's trained in biology and
he studies the patterns of history using
mathematical models and what he does in
this book is he explores the way that
empires have risen and fallen over time
and the way that the internal cohesion
of social groups enable large-scale
collective action so this is a book
about the mathematical patterns of
history kind of a complexity science of
the history of civilizations and I found
it to be extremely useful for me because
I want to understand how different
groups of people can come together form
shared social identities and then start
to work together in collaborative ways
against other human groups to achieve
large goals and so this book looks at
such factors as the way that inequality
can arise within a social group and how
that inequality can lead to the
breakdown of cooperation and then there
could be things like noble elites can
start to battle against each other while
the poor are marginalized that might
sound familiar to what's happening in
the world today so this kind of a
dynamic pattern where a group of people
come together and form an increasingly
complex civilization then have internal
dynamics of cohesion and coherence as
well as tension and conflict and the
patterns that arise between those
different drivers are what enables
civilizations to rise and ultimately
caused them to collapse so what Peter
Turchin does in this book that I think
is really really helpful for change
strategists today is he offers a
framework for understanding how the
competition between different groups
specifically the frontier region at the
edge of Empires where there are bands of
tribal groups that end up in
battles and conflict with the Empire how
that can create internal cohesion within
the Empire that enables it to remain
strong so we might think of this in
terms of a the current context looking
at things like the the rise of the Tea
Party in the United States and how it is
a small but very internal a cohesive
group and as it engages an ideological
battle for the kind of the territory of
the mind for politics in the United
States how the the liberal or the
progressive groups that compete with the
Tea Party ideology can actually create a
a type of frontier boundary effect that
helps to a strengthen the internal
cohesion of that group so this is how
the Roman Empire was able to rise and
persist for a thousand years this is how
various empires in Eastern Europe and in
South America were able to rise and
remain coherent at boundaries with other
human tribal communities and it's also
how political tribes and economic tribes
today can form empires of a great
sophistication so so what we really need
to do is understand how those patterns
arise and this is a book it'll help you
understand how that works so I think
that if you want to understand the large
scale patterns of civilization and how
to create group cohesion to achieve
collective goals then you'll want to
read this book so that's it um we're on
peace and war by Peter Turkson enjoy